Frank C. Laubach Collection
Frank C. Laubach Collection
1896-1974
Laubach, Frank Charles, 1884-1970.
211.5 linear ft.
Personal papers of the missionary, adult educator, and literacy pioneer; also contains organizational records of Laubach Literacy, Inc. Collection includes correspondence, administrative papers, financial papers, U.S. and international projects, writings, photographs, and miscellanea.
2649905
Biographical History
Frank C. Laubach (1884-1970) was a Christian Evangelical missionary, author, and educator who specialized in international literacy. Dr. Laubach recognized literacy as a "first step toward ending the suffering and exploitation of the world's disadvantaged" (Laubach Literacy International brochure); he was the founder of the "Each One Teach One" literacy teaching method and of Laubach Literacy, and is credited with teaching more than 100 million people to read."
Frank C. Laubach
Frank Charles Laubach was born in Benton, Pennsylvania on September 2, 1884. He studied at Bloomsburg State College (1901), Perkiomen Prep School (1905), Princeton University (BA, 1909), and Union Theological Seminary (1913). He was married to Effa Seely on May 15, 1912, and earned his MA (1912) and PhD (1915) from Columbia University.
In 1915, Dr. Laubach and his wife went to the Philippines as Congregational missionaries with the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. He was a minister at Cagayan, and taught at Union Theological Seminary in Manila. In 1930, he began literacy work on the island of Mindanao and developed an alphabet for the Maranaws in their own Maranaw language. This was the start of his "Each One Teach One" concept, which encouraged adults taught by the system to then volunteer their time to teach others. From 1930 to 1970, Dr. Laubach traveled to more than one hundred countries developing literacy primers in 312 languages. He and his literacy teams worked with missions, private agencies, governments, U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID), the Peace Corps, and UNESCO.
In 1935 Dr. Laubach organized the World Literacy Committee, and in 1941 he became one of the founders of the Committee on World Literacy and Christian Literature, known as "Lit-Lit" (later Intermedia) of the National Council of Churches. He worked with this organization until his retirement in 1954 at the age of 70. In 1951, to facilitate cooperation with government and secular organizations, Dr. Laubach started World Literacy, Inc. (now World Education). In 1955, the year after his retirement, he founded Laubach Literacy, Inc., a non-profit literacy organization with headquarters in Syracuse, New York. His son, Robert, took over the presidency of LLI after Dr. Laubach's death on June 11, 1970. Mrs. Effa Laubach died on March 29, 1973, at the age of 85; the couple are buried in the family plot in Benton, Pennsylvania.
Dr. Laubach was a prolific writer whose books covered a variety of interests, including the Philippines, prayer and spiritual life, challenges to world literacy and to international technical assistance, and materials to teach adults to read (including literacy primers in 312 languages). He gave the impetus to the opening of literacy and journalism courses at Hartford School of Missions, Syracuse University, Asbury College, Baylor University, University of California, and more than twenty other centers across the United States.
Laubach has been recognized many times for his accomplishments. He received honorary degrees from Princeton, Columbia, Syracuse, and Temple Universities, and from Lafayette, Wooster, Muskingam, Marietta, Findlay, and Baldwin-Wallace Colleges. Time magazine referred to him as the founder of a world-wide literacy drive. Norman Vincent Peale, in Look, called Laubach one of the five greatest men in the world, and Newsweek featured him as "one of the grand men of the missionary world." Lowell Thomas called him "the foremost teacher of our times." On the 100th anniversary of his birth, the United States Postal Service honored Dr. Laubach with the issue of a commemorative stamp in the "Great Americans" series.
Four books have been written about him: Apostle to the Illiterates, by David E. Mason; Each One Teach One, by Marjorie Medary; Champion of the Silent Billion, by Helen M. Roberts; and Frank C. Laubach, Teacher of Millions, by David E. Mason. His work has been taught to Sunday School children in the curriculum of the Methodist, Lutheran, and other denominations. Dozens of religious and secular magazines including Together, The Lutheran Standard, Christian Herald, Time, Look, Newsweek, Reader's Digest, Collier's, and Saturday Evening Post have run articles about "Mr. Literacy."
Laubach Literacy, Inc.
For a detailed history of Laubach Literacy and related organizations, including the National Affilication for Literacy Advance (NALA), Laubach Literacy Action (LLA), New Readers Press (NRP), and ProLiteracy Worldwide, please refer to the
Laubach Literacy, Inc. Records
finding aid.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Frank C. Laubach Collection contains both the organizational papers of Laubach Literacy, Inc. (LLI) and the personal papers of Frank C. Laubach. The collection traces the development of literacy teaching from the early 1920's, at the beginning of Dr. Laubach's missionary career with the Moro tribe in the Philippines, and reaches into the present efforts of Laubach Literacy, Inc., to deal with illiteracy on a worldwide scale. As such, it is a valuable research tool for students of literacy in America or of world literacy.
The collection includes correspondence, personal papers of both Frank and Effa Laubach, administrative papers, financial papers, writings (manuscripts and articles), organizational and meeting material, and photographs, as well as material relating to trustees, domestic and international projects, languages, and some miscellany.
Correspondence, the first major group of the Laubach Collection, is divided into four subgroups: Frank Laubach, General, Foreign, and Specific files. Dr. Laubach's own correspondence dates are considerably earlier than the other sub-groups. General correspondence contains organizational correspondence of a varied nature, covering the broad range of questions concerning Laubach Literacy, Inc. Foreign correspondence pertains to foreign correspondence of such a general nature that it has no specific file. Specific files contains the correspondence of specific individuals and projects.
The next series, Frank C. Laubach papers, consist of a great variety of material accumulated over Dr. Laubach's lifetime: biographical material; essays, articles and speeches; scrapbooks and diaries, manuscripts dated before 1955. The notes, memorabilia and data collected during Dr. Laubach's missionary career in the Philippines are of particular philosophical and historical interest.
The papers of Laubach's wife, Effa Seely Laubach (1882-1973), consist of a small amount of correspondence and miscellaneous notes.
Trustees' material consists of agenda, meetings, minutes of meetings and decisions concerning the Board of Trustees of Laubach Literacy, Inc.
Administrative files are divided into two subgroups. Administrative papers consists of major materials regarding organizational policy, contracts and personnel information. Administrative correspondence is all interoffice memoranda within and from Laubach Literacy, Inc.
Financial papers include budgets, auditors' reports, bank statements and corporate assessments.
Projects, domestic consist of literacy programs, projects, and training workshops sponsored by Laubach Literacy in the United States. Included here is National Affiliation for Literacy Advance (NALA) material as well as the papers and records of state and local literacy organizations.
Projects, overseas contains material related to literacy projects abroad, such as U.S. Government (AID, Peace Corps) contracts, proposals, and support; and monthly reports from Laubach staff members located in other countries.
Languages contain all the primers and reading materials developed or used by Laubach in any language. More than 300 languages are represented.
Manuscripts and articles contain the manuscripts developed at Laubach Literacy, Inc., from 1955 to 1969. This group also holds other manuscripts and articles prepared by Laubach staff members or interested persons.
Organizations and meetings contains the records and papers of organizations, conferences and meetings not directly sponsored by Laubach Literacy, but of interest to Laubach staff members or Trustees.
Miscellaneous holds over six boxes of newspaper clippings collected at Laubach Literacy, and also includes unclassified newsletters and pamphlets.
Photographs relate to a variety of Laubach projects, both domestic and overseas, and are filed by geographical location. Also included are photographs of the Laubach family.
The collection closes with 99 Streamlined Reading films covering lessons in literacy instruction.
Arrangement of the Collection
The subdivisions of Correspondence are arranged chronologically except for Specific files, which are alphabetical by name. All remaining series are arranged alphabetically by name, title, or topic as appropriate.
Related Material
See also the
Laubach Literacy International Records
. In addition, the library has many published works by Frank Laubach; please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Religion and philosophy; Laubach, Effa S., 1882-1973.; Laubach, Frank Charles, 1884-1970.; Laubach, Robert S (Robert Seely), 1918-; Mason, David E.; Laubach Literacy, Inc.; Adult education -- United States.; Adult education teachers -- Training of.; Clergy -- United States.; Clergy as authors.; Educators -- United States.; English language -- Study and teaching -- Foreign speakers.; English language -- Textbooks for foreign speakers.; Evening and continuation schools -- United States.; Literacy.; Literacy -- Africa.; Literacy -- Asia.; Literacy -- Colombia.; Literacy -- India.; Literacy -- Latin America.; Literacy -- Mexico.; Literacy -- United States.; Missionaries.; New literates, Writing for.; Television in adult education.; Visual literacy.; Articles.; Bank statements.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Essays.; Financial records.; Manuscripts for publication.; Maps (documents); Motion pictures (visual works); Newsletters.; Photographs.; Poems.; Progress reports.; Proposals.; Readers.; Reports.; Minutes (administrative records); Textbooks.; Adult education teachers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Majority gift of Frank C. Laubach, 1966-1978.
Material in boxes 328A, 328B and 328C, gift of David Mason, 2011.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Laubach, Frank
    - 1896-1932, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - 1933-1938, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - 1940-1954, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 1955, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - 1956 Jan-1957 May, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - 1957 Jun-Dec, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - 1958 Jan-1959 Feb, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - 1959 Mar-1960 Feb, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - 1960 Mar-Sep, 5 folders (Box 9)
    - 1960 Oct-1961 Aug, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - 1961 Sep-1962 Sep, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - 1962 Oct-1963 Jun, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - 1963 Jul-1964 Mar, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - 1964 Apr-Oct, 4 folders (Box 14)
    - 1964 Nov-1965 Apr, 5 folders (Box 15)
    - 1965 May-Sep, 5 folders (Box 16)
    - 1965 Oct-Dec, 5 folders (Box 17)
    - 1965 Dec-1966 Mar, 5 folders (Box 18)
    - 1966 Apr-Jul, 5 folders (Box 19)
    - 1966 Aug-Oct, 7 folders (Box 20)
    - 1966 Nov-1967 Dec, 5 folders (Box 21)
    - 1968 Jan-Sep, 5 folders (Box 22)
    - 1968 Oct-1969 Aug, 6 folders (Box 23)
    - 1969 Sep-1971, undated; 6 folders (Box 24)
    - Sympathy letters
      - 1970, 4 folders (Box 25)
      - 1970, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - General
    - 1940-1960 Feb, 6 folders (Box 27)
    - 1960 Mar-Aug, 6 folders (Box 28)
    - 1960 Sep-1961 Feb, 5 folders (Box 29)
    - 1961 Mar-Jun, 6 folders (Box 30)
    - 1961 Jul-Oct, 7 folders (Box 31)
    - 1961 Oct-Dec, 6 folders (Box 32)
    - 1961 Dec-1962 Jan, 6 folders (Box 33)
    - 1962 Jan-Mar, 6 folders (Box 34)
    - 1962 Mar-Apr, 6 folders (Box 35)
    - 1962 Apr-Jun, 6 folders (Box 36)
    - 1962 Jun-Jul, 6 folders (Box 37)
    - 1962 Aug-Sep, 6 folders (Box 38)
    - 1962 Oct-Nov, 5 folders (Box 39)
    - 1962 Dec-1963 Jan, 5 folders (Box 40)
    - 1963 Jan-Mar, 5 folders (Box 41)
    - 1963 Mar-May, 6 folders (Box 42)
    - 1963 May-Jul, 7 folders (Box 43)
    - 1963 Aug-Oct, 7 folders (Box 44)
    - 1963 Nov-1964 Jan, 6 folders (Box 45)
    - 1964 Feb-Apr, 5 folders (Box 46)
    - 1964 Apr-Jun, 5 folders (Box 47)
    - 1964 Jul-Sep, 6 folders (Box 48)
    - 1964 Oct-Nov, 4 folders (Box 49)
    - 1964 Dec-1965 Feb, 6 folders (Box 50)
    - 1965 Feb-Mar, 5 folders (Box 51)
    - 1965 Apr-May, 5 folders (Box 52)
    - 1965 Jun-Aug, 4 folders (Box 53)
    - 1965 Aug-Oct, 6 folders (Box 54)
    - 1965 Oct-Dec, 6 folders (Box 55)
    - 1966 Jan-Feb, 5 folders (Box 56)
    - 1966 Mar-Apr, 5 folders (Box 57)
    - 1966 Apr-Jun, 6 folders (Box 58)
    - 1966 Jun-Aug, 6 folders (Box 59)
    - 1966 Sep-Nov, 5 folders (Box 60)
    - 1966 Nov-1967 Jan, 5 folders (Box 61)
    - 1967 Jan-Feb, 5 folders (Box 62)
    - 1967 Feb-Apr, 6 folders (Box 63)
    - 1967 Apr-Jun, 6 folders (Box 64)
    - 1967 Jul-Sep, 6 folders (Box 65)
    - 1967 Oct-Nov, 5 folders (Box 66)
    - 1967 Dec-1968 Feb, 5 folders (Box 67)
    - 1968 Feb-Mar, 4 folders (Box 68)
    - 1968 Mar-May, 5 folders (Box 69)
    - 1968 Jun-Aug, 6 folders (Box 70)
    - 1968 Sep-Nov, 5 folders (Box 71)
    - 1968 Dec-1969 Jan, 5 folders (Box 72)
    - 1969 Feb-Apr, 5 folders (Box 73)
    - 1969 Apr-Jun, 4 folders (Box 74)
    - 1969 Jun-Sep, 5 folders (Box 75)
    - 1969 Sep-Nov, 5 folders (Box 76)
    - 1969 Dec-1970 Apr, 6 folders (Box 77)
    - 1970 May-Oct, 5 folders (Box 78)
    - 1970 Nov-1972, 3 folders (Box 79)
    - Undated (Box 79)
  - Foreign, general
    - 1951-1961 Sep, 6 folders (Box 80)
    - 1961 Oct-1962 Jul, 5 folders (Box 81)
    - 1962 Aug-1964 Jun, 6 folders (Box 82)
    - 1964 Jul-1967, 5 folders (Box 83)
    - 1968-1970, 3 folders (Box 84)
  - Specific files
    - Boyer, Gilbert
      - 1960-1964 Apr, 6 folders (Box 85)
      - 1964 May -1969, 2 folders (Box 86)
    - Caswell, Robert, 1964-1970 (Box 86)
    - Chapman, Margaret, 1957-1967 (Box 86)
    - Colombia, 1962-1969; 2 folders (Box 86)
    - Dames, Joseph J.
      - 1960-1963 (Box 86)
      - 1964-1970, 2 folders (Box 87)
    - Ecuador (Box 87)
    - Edwards, Fern, 1961-1967 (Box 87)
    - Friedman, Robert
      - 1962-1965 (Box 87)
      - 1965-1970 (Box 88)
    - Giffin, George, 1967-1968 (Box 88)
    - Gipson, Priscilla, 1961-1970; 3 folders (Box 88)
    - Guatemala, 1962-1965; 2 folders (Box 88)
    - Haynes, Evelyn, 1962-1967 (Box 88)
    - Henry, William, 1964-1966 (Box 89)
    - High, Ellen, 1958-1965 (Box 89)
    - Hudkins, James, 1968 (Box 89)
    - Johannes, Phyllis, 1962-1969; 3 folders (Box 89)
    - John, A. K., 1958-1970; 2 folders (Box 89)
    - Johnson, Marion, 1942-1970 (Box 90)
    - Jordan, 1960-1967 (Box 90)
    - Kirk, Elizabeth M., 1962-1963 (Box 90)
    - Koinonia Foundation, 1952-1969; 3 folders (Box 90)
    - Leonard, Benjamin, 1961-1963 (Box 91)
    - Likins, Robert, 1959-1966 (Box 91)
    - Lowe, Lorenzo
      - 1956-1960 Jun, 5 folders (Box 91)
      - 1960 Jul-1961 Sep, 6 folders (Box 92)
      - 1961 Oct-1962 Dec, 3 folders (Box 93)
      - Undated (Box 93)
    - Macmillan, May
      - 1957-1962, 3 folders (Box 93)
      - 1963-1967, 6 folders (Box 94)
      - 1968-1970 (Box 95)
    - Mason, David
      - to Frank Laubach, 1963-1968; undated; 3 folders (Box 328B)
      - to Bob Laubach, 1967 (Box 328B)
    - Mexico, 1958-1967; 3 folders (Box 95)
    - Morgan, Angela, 1940-1957 (Box 95)
    - Morrill, Louise
      - 1959-1962, 4 folders (Box 95)
      - 1963-1970 (Box 96)
    - Oliver-Douglas, 1959-1966 (Box 96)
    - Pakistan, East
      - 1955-1962, 2 folders (Box 96)
      - 1963-1968 (Box 97)
    - Peace Corps, 1961-1968; 6 folders (Box 97)
    - Pearson, Irving, 1962-1968; 6 folders (Box 98)
    - Philippines, 1933-1965 (Box 98)
    - Pitts, Edward, 1968-1970 (Box 98)
    - Roberts, Byron T., 1961-1969; 3 folders (Box 99)
    - Roberts, Helen, 1958-1964 (Box 99)
    - Sabo, Joseph, 1961-1968; 3 folders (Box 99)
    - Shumate, Hazel
      - 1960-1963 (Box 99)
      - 1964-1969, 2 folders (Box 100)
    - Smith, Dorita, 1960-1963 (Box 100)
    - U.S. Government Departments
      - 1948-1962, 3 folders (Box 100)
      - 1963-1970, 5 folders (Box 101)
    - U.S. Government, elected representatives, 1957-1970; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - U.S. Government, literacy proposal to, 1961-1962 (Box 102)
    - Valle de Bravo, 1957-1968; 2 folders (Box 102)
    - Vestermark, Lynne, 1962-1963 (Box 102)
    - Ward, Muriel B. (Box 102)
    - Warlow, Loretta, 1959-1967 (Box 103)
    - Whittington, Richard, 1962 (Box 103)
    - Willard, Jay, 1967-1968 (Box 103)
- Laubach, Frank
  - Accounts, 1945-1957 (Box 104)
  - Addresses (Box 104)
  - Africa (Box 104)
  - Art work (Box 104)
  - Articles
    - I-III, 3 folders (Box 104)
    - IV-VII, 4 folders (Box 105)
    - VIII (Box 106)
  - Articles by, 4 folders (Box 106)
  - Articles by, The Argus (Box 107)
  - Articles about
    - I-II, 2 folders (Box 107)
    - III-VI, 4 folders (Box 108)
    - VII-IX, 3 folders (Box 109)
  - Australia, 1949 (Box 109)
  - Bibliographies (Box 109)
  - Biographical data (Box 109)
  - Birthday banquets (Box 110)
  - Book manuscript, parts of (Box 110)
  - Book reviews, 2 folders (Box 110)
  - Books for the People (Box 110)
  - Broadcasts (Box 110)
  - Camps Farthest Out (Box 110)
  - "Christ Liveth in Me" (Box 110)
  - "Christian Save Your World", draft (Box 110)
  - Church statistics (Box 110)
  - Can I Help You (CIHU), 1947-1955 (Box 110)
  - Committee on World Literacy and Christian Literature, 1942-1954 (Box 110)
  - "Compassion of Jesus as Told by Matthew" (Box 111)
  - Courses: Literacy as Evangelism, 1969 (Box 111)
  - Daily devotions, 1952 (Box 111)
  - Death of, notes sent and received (Box 111)
  - Diaries and notes
    - 1921-1938, 4 folders (Box 111)
    - 1937-1940, 5 bound volumes (Box 328A)
    - 1939-1970, 3 folders (Box 112)
    - 1953, 1 volume (Box 328A)
  - Diaries from the Philippines, 1929-1940 (Box 112)
  - "Did Mary Tell Jesus Her Secret?", foreword (Box 112)
  - Directories, 1928-1933 (Box 112)
  - "Each One Teach One," Educational Significance of, 1970 (Box 113)
  - Economy, world, 1953-1954 (Box 113)
  - Egypt (Box 113)
  - Essays
    - I-IV, 4 folders (Box 113)
    - V-IX, 5 folders (Box 114)
    - X-XV, 6 folders (Box 115)
    - XVI-XI, 4 folders (Box 116)
  - Essays about (Box 116)
  - Evangelism, personal (Box 116)
  - "Far East Newsletter", 1949 (Box 116)
  - Foreign aid, 1953-1954 (Box 116)
  - Form letters, 2 folders (Box 117)
  - "Forty Years with the Silent Billion"
    - Chapters 1-146, 3 folders (Box 117)
    - Chapters 47-60, 3 folders (Box 118)
    - Recording 1-23, 2 folders (Box 118)
  - Genealogy (Box 119)
  - Gospel of Mark (Box 119)
  - "Growing Bigger Every Day", 1961 (Box 119)
  - "How to Make the World Literate", 1957; 2 folders (Box 119)
  - India, 1949-1956 (Box 119)
  - Indonesian Literacy Conference, 1951 (Box 119)
  - Inspired Letters (Box 119)
  - Interviews (Box 119)
  - Inter-American Affairs (Box 119)
  - Itineraries
    - I-II, 2 folders (Box 119)
    - III-IV, 2 folders (Box 120)
  - Journalism, re, 1953-1954 (Box 120)
  - Journals, 1939 (Box 120)
  - Key system for teaching illiterates (Box 120)
  - "Lanao Progress"
    - 1933-1935, 2 folders (Box 120)
    - 1936-1941 (Box 121)
  - "Last Ten Years" (Box 121)
  - Laubach method, comment on the, 1966 (Box 121)
  - Laymen's Movement for A Christian World, Inc., 2 folders (Box 121)
  - "Letters From A Modern Mystic" unedited manuscript (Box 121)
  - Liberia, 1952 (Box 121)
  - Library lists, suggest (Box 121)
  - Libya, 1951 (Box 121)
  - Literacy, articles re (Box 122)
  - Literacy campaign in India and Africa, 1936-1937 (Box 122)
  - Literacy evangelism (Box 122)
  - Magazines, 1946; 1956-1969 (Box 122)
  - Mailing addresses, 1932-1940 (Box 122)
  - "Making Everybody's World Safe" (Box 122)
  - Malaya visits, 1952 (Box 122)
  - Manuscript, untitled, 1943 (Box 122)
  - Maps (Box 123)
  - Meals for Millions Foundation (Box 123)
  - Memorabilia
    - 1910-1951 (Box 123)
    - 1954 (Box 123)
    - 1956-1964, includes birthday tributes; 4 folders (Box 124)
    - 1965-1968, 4 folders (Box 125)
    - 1970 (Box 126)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 126)
  - Moro book
    - Draft, 1930-1933 (Box 126)
    - Notes for, 1915 (Box 126)
  - New Guinea, 1949 (Box 126)
  - The new literacy method, 1949 (Box 126)
  - New literates, preparing material for, 1951 (Box 126)
  - News releases, 1946-1965 (Box 126)
  - Notes
    - 1904-1921, 1927, 1937, 1945-1949, 1951-1969, 6 folders (Box 127)
    - 1970 (Box 128)
    - Undated
  - Pamphlets
    - I-II, 2 folders (Box 128)
    - III-IV, 2 folders (Box 129)
  - Paris Prayer Groups, 1946 (Box 129)
  - Passports (Box 129)
  - Peace proposal, Philippines, 1934 (Box 129)
  - Philippines
    - [General], 1920-1929 (Box 129)
    - [General], 1930-1966; 4 folders (Box 130)
    - Accounts in, 1930-1940 (Box 130)
    - Articles from (Box 131)
    - Cooperating Committee for Philippines (Box 131)
    - Islam in (Box 131)
    - Literacy in (Box 131)
    - Society of Educated Youth of, 1934 (Box 131)
    - United Evangelical Church, 1933 (Box 131)
  - Plays (Box 131)
  - Poems (Box 131)
  - Point Four (Box 131)
  - Portraits of (Box 131)
  - Portuguese primer (Box 131)
  - "The Positive Thing", draft (Box 131)
  - Prayers
    - I (Box 131)
    - II-III, 2 folders (Box 132)
  - Programs
    - I-II, 2 folders (Box 132)
    - III-V, 3 folders (Box 133)
  - Promotion for Laubach Literacy Advance (Box 133)
  - Publications (Box 133)
  - Recognition of (Box 133)
  - "Rollcall" Yearbook, 1962 (Box 134)
  - Royalties, statements of (Box 134)
  - "Shut Your Eyes", manuscript (Box 134)
  - "The Silent Billion", draft (Box 134)
  - The Silent League, 1929-1930 (Box 134)
  - Songs (Box 134)
  - Speeches and sermons
    - I-III, 3 folders (Box 134)
    - IV-VIII, 5 folders (Box 135)
    - IX-XI, 3 folders (Box 136)
  - Spelling, new, 2 folders (Box 136)
  - Spelling reform
    - I (Box 136)
    - II-VI, 5 folders (Box 137)
    - VII (Box 138)
  - Statement re, 1947-1964 (Box 138)
  - "Story ov Je/sus Re/told from thu Bi/bl, thu," part one, 1960 (Box 138)
  - Supplies, missionary (Box 138)
  - "Teaching the World to Read"
    - Chapters 7-23, 1946 (Box 138)
    - Bibliography, 1946 (Box 138)
  - Tours, 1944-1970 (Box 138)
  - Tours, letters from
    - 1933-1944 (Box 138)
    - 1947-1966 (Box 138)
    - 1960-1967 (Box 139)
  - Travel papers (Box 139)
  - United Nations (Box 139)
  - U.S. Government (Box 139)
  - "Was Jesus Really God's Son?", manuscript (Box 139)
  - Who's Who in the East (Box 139)
  - "Why and How", 1967 (Box 139)
  - World Health Organization, 1953-1955 (Box 139)
  - World Literacy, Inc.
    - I-II, 2 folders (Box 139)
    - III-IV, 3 folders (Box 140)
  - World Neighbors, Inc. (Box 140)
  - World Outreach, 1969 (Box 140)
  - World peace, 2 folders (Box 140)
  - Yiddish primer (Box 141)
  - "You are My Friends", 1942; draft (Box 141)
- Laubach, Effa Seeley
  - Correspondence, 1915-1972; 3 folders (Box 142)
  - Notes and various material, 2 folders (Box 142)
- Trustees
  - Committees (Box 143)
  - Financial reports, 1957-1971; 2 folders (Box 143)
  - Letters to, 1959-1969 (Box 143)
  - Meetings
    - 1961-1966, 11 folders (Box 143)